Um, now Nick, you've been a software
developer for actually pretty much as
long as I have now. Just uh about 20
years or so, a couple of decades.
You work for EPAM in the Netherlands,
been software engineer all the way
through to head of development, and
you're leading huge development teams,
right? Uh, yeah. Yeah, I I've been
working in it all my life in software
and it's amazing times now with
everything which is changing. The whole
software development life cycle is
changing and I'm super pumped to be part
of it. Yeah. Awesome. Awesome. And you
also you you work on a um an open source
project
um Refact AI uh which you built I
believe with a previous OpenAI
researcher. Is that correct? Yeah, very
much true. Yeah, we uh we're developing
an uh open source um open source uh
agent and and code assistant. The things
are kind of blending these days anyway.
Uh yeah, so very exciting to talk a
little bit about that as well. Uh and
how we applying that uh work and how we
apply the fine tunes. Well, Nick, it's a
pleasure to have you on stage with us.
Um I'll pass it over to you and uh
looking forward to hearing what you've
got to say in and around the fine tuning
space. Thank you very much. Um again
Simon done all the work for me in terms
of intro introducing myself. So uh all
all the uh things which needs to be said
are set. Uh the last thing is uh it's
just you missed my uh very uh funny
tagline in X. So um add the wipe coder
to one of the follows out there. Um and
yes and it Refact is an open-source AI
agent and assistant. Uh we uh uh the
company has been founded by former open
eye researcher. Uh we got featured by uh
Gartner Magic Quadrant, partnered with
AWS. Uh featured with Deepseek,
Infocrunch, all the other guys. Very
proud with our uh more recent results
and benchmarking on SW benchmarks. We
already submitted our uh pull requests
uh into the S.WE.
So looking forward to be added and you
already can read um details on that on
our website. Now uh yes and we are uh uh
very proud to work with number of large
enterprises.
Um so um what I'm going to talk today
about is indeed fine-tune um going to
talk about code completion going to talk
about some of the use cases agents.
Hopefully we'll have um uh some good Q&A
there. Um and the kind of the challenge
for me with the setups like this is um I
have all the um anxiety of being a
presenter on stage but I don't have the
audience uh responses. So uh bear with
me at the comments as you go. I'll try
to look at all this uh in the end of the
session. Um yeah so um again kind of the
assumption which I had going into this
talk usually I talk about how the agents
work how um our tool works inside out um
and today I was asked to talk uh a
little bit more specifically about uh
the finetune cases so for those who um
um kind of not really familiar with that
let me um take uh take you um um and
explain uh that a little bit details. So
as we all know the large models are
large for a reason uh because they
trained on on gazillion of data and uh
the example here which I have that for
example written llama 4 uh not even the
the biggest one being trained for yeah
an equivalent of seven and a half
million of hours on on the um on a GPU.
So it's a big task to train that. We
obviously uh most of our mu mortals
cannot uh do that. But what we can do is
we able to um adjust some part of it
right customize some behavior of the
model um um and see how we can better
use the capabilities. And in general by
using the existing openw weight
pre-trained models uh we can uh improve
performance for specific tasks without
kind of uh breaking the bank with all
the computational resources required for
that. To do that there is a um clever um
uh mass uh in works in play. Uh if
someone is asking a question am I
showing linear algebra? Yes I am. Uh so
the very basic idea uh behind this
cleric trick is to use a smaller matrix
um uh uh smaller matrices which uh store
the adjustments to the weights of the
open models and then applies this
weights either on the fly or uh uh kind
of freconer. So
um I'm not going to go and kind of walk
you through lines of code which show you
exactly how to run PyTorch or how
exactly run um hugging face
transformers. There is plenty of tools
out there uh for it. There is even
better uh kind of tools today which
allows you to do fine tunes. Uh I
mentioned some of them here. I really
like um um for example Anslaught the
documentation they have. They have
really deep coverage on how to prepare
your data for fine-tunes uh all the
different data sets and details and they
also allow you to uh to do it with a um
fairly low resources uh doing some
clever tricks to run it even on your
laptop. Transformer Lab has a nice UI as
well to uh to help you um create data
sets um even with use of
LLMs. Um and yeah when we talk about uh
the closed models even the closed models
allow us to uh to add some itune. So,
open eye had uh fine tubes jobs API from
the beginning of time. An entropic uh uh
offer some support of fine tunes via AWS
and for example Mistral um also
providing the support and the best part
about what they do which I really like
is they allow uh they don't really uh
change the price of uh running your
finetunes model. So there is no
difference between was I using their
model as it is or fine-tune. Um so
that's kind of a nice uh thing about
it. Now and again um I think fine tunes
have kind of a bad rep and one of that
is um because it takes um yeah a lot of
time and money and and uh effort to
prepare the um uh the data. uh well it
used to uh but now we living in a time
where we can uh generate synthetic data
we can generate data uh with the use of
advanced LLMs and uh from that create a
data sets which we use to fine-tune and
again the data sets is essentially the
examples of what we telling the model is
right behavior and um sometimes we even
can add the wrong behavior and we
usually then test those examples with
the uh uh with a loss function and
here's a example of a loss curve and
then we split them to see if our
behavior is adjusted to desired but um
also um need to be done with caution
because um there are a number of papers
and the one which I'm um studying right
here on on the screen is um the one
which um basically mentioned that while
we align the behavior of our models
while our uh loss curve is uh moving in
the direction we want. We also um
override and and make the the model uh
forget the behavior. So the takeaway
from that is the fine-tune models which
we created um should be used for only in
this particular use cases which we
created for and not uh used as your um
uh general uh model for your main
agentic use
cases. Um all right. So let's jump right
into that. So uh finetune for code
completion. So again code completion is
very much a new thing. It's kind of
intellency uh intellisense on a steroid.
It's a completion of the lines um in
your project uh in for example in your
file right in your ID um as one of the
use cases which are very often used
today and it's done with a a special
kind of models. Usually it will be
fairly small model uh the ones which are
optimized for speed because if you use a
large chat model for this purpose you
will have a really long uh
latency and you would need to wait for a
long time. Um so normally uh the uh the
models which you see are um especially
in all the open source projects are
derivatives of one of the those which I
mentioned here right the deepc quarter
quen quarter cholesterol star codel
those uh families of models are had been
trained on a large uh data sets and uh
have amazing performance to speed in
terms of how they um how they
Um yeah so the downside of how the
models been trained is uh the fact that
um they train on the average uh let's
say open repositories and that's great
on average again but uh when it starts
to um suggest you um pieces of code uh
they might be um maybe slightly less
relevant. Maybe you have your own
standards on how you doing the login you
do uh login you uh have own standards
how you doing um uh yes the security
patterns you name it. Usually if you
take average enterprise and look at
their
um uh the microservices set you will see
that all the microservices are pretty
much a boiler plate with some um logic
added on top of it. So um it will be
nice if our um code completion models
are actually being able to capture this
boiler plate and use it.
Um all right so um again as part of
refaci we have a kind of complex uh tool
set but one of one of them is beside the
agentic part which actually done all the
work we have the the server side which
can use models and can actually help
with performance of fine tunes in our
particular case what we allowed to do
and this is a kind of a screenshot from
um part of the uh UI for this experience
But the screenshot is basically um yeah
um shows um that we select number of
different projects which we have and
then uh select the the target model
which we use as um
um to fine-tune further on and that's um
actually
um
uh really a really helpful setup. how
does it work from inside of it. So um
behind the scenes uh when we're doing
the data set preparation um for the
finetuning of the codebase um so we
obviously took the the codebase files um
in our tool set we have the idea of the
privacy guide uh guardrails if by some
reason in some files you decided to
store your passwords SSH keys tokens uh
whatever uh yeah those files are added
uh as those which are excluded from the
um uh fine-tuning uh process. We
obviously then have a selections based
of the relevant extension and the size
of the files removing binary files,
removing the large JSON and whatnot. Uh
we also remove the external vendors if
we're able to identify them through um
the company license files like that uh
or license heaters and then we also uh
remove PI data. We have some some um
yeah fairly simple algorithms which try
to remove emails and stuff like that
from that. And just like that uh we uh
get ourself a data set from um all
different code base which um uh our
customers or users have. We prepare we
split them in chunks based on um the
desired tokens. Usually it might be
something like around um 2,000 uh uh
tokens or so uh with some overlap which
helps uh model to to kind of look at it
from a uh different sides. Um those
chunks are usually shuffled and then
this is how they kind of the data
prepared for that. But again like I said
already we live in the um golden time
for the um uh for data set preparation.
And even better way is uh if you can
afford it is to actually run the LL
model from uh through these pieces of
code and put in the inline comments. And
those inline comments will uh be really
helpful uh from uh when you yourself
would want to um type something in and
ask a code completion model to finish it
for you. Um all right. So um code
completion is kind of not really the
most exciting part today. um everyone
excited about using of agents and using
of tools and this is where
uh uh one of the next use cases which I
have have so uh we had an a case where
we needed to um connect the agent with a
large um database so normally right as
you've seen in many articles online and
blogs post and so on or even using
yourself in chat GPT you can just add
tables definition right there. But if
there are hundreds uh tables across
multiple databases in terabytes, how do
we make sure that we make a performant
um um performant queries? So the first
part is again uh the data preparation
right and this is where LLM serves uh
immense value. Um in most of the
examples online you would see that um uh
the people assume that the kind of
tables and columns in your database are
self-explanatory. That's not always the
case. Um um and uh this is was our case
in this particular uh story. Um so we
had to um analyze every column in every
table write um additional details about
it. We're kind of doing the um yeah um
exploration of what type of data in
there. Uh going all the way crazy uh
crazy ways to then write um even details
about the uh try to infer details about
the relationship between the tables and
the descriptions of that.
So, um, all of that, uh, led us to being
able to, um, uh, then put this data into
some semantic search, uh, some sort of a
rack search where we can add tools for
our agent to find relevant tables and
also have a more simple way to ask
details about particular table. And we
also added ability to actually run some
queries. Um in some cases it was very
useful as well but um uh be careful to
put the guardrail uh guard rails in such
cases as run on lists and uh doing on um
timeouts.
So um we now able to generate queries
but the generation of them slow right uh
we have many tool calls we limited by
the architecture of rock uh which is top
end there might be some missing tables
not return to um the context and also
the models can generate kind of a slow
um uh poor joints and unoptimal requests
to our database. So we decided to go and
look at it from an other side out. So we
took a log of actual production queries
which was millions and millions of
queries. We duplicate them and actually
ask our agent now to do the uh the
opposite solve the opposite task. So uh
explain for each query from our
production database uh what was uh the
query tries to do. Now that our agent
have ability to go and look at the
tables and have a definition of tables
from that we actually create a really
nice uh training data set for our fine
tune and uh again the things which um at
least uh was relevant here uh is um yeah
in your real production you will have
some more usage of particular tables and
less usage of other tables. So we had to
kind of uh look at the distribution
making sure that all the all the
relevant tables um uh are in there. So
yeah from that we created the
uh the uh the subset and uh use it for
fine-tune. All right.
Um and um essentially what we did we put
this whole um SQL generation um into um
a a special tool called text to your
scale tool uh behind which uh the agent
was basically routing requests to our uh
special small fine tetone LLMs which now
has been blazingly fast and has been
provided a lot of relevant uh requests
uh for us. Um so that's kind of has been
one of the kind of in-depth cases on
that. Um we still can add other tools if
we want but we need to make sure that uh
uh uh we tell in system prompt or uh to
our agent that uh yeah the uh first we
try to use this tool and then if it
doesn't work then we try to fix it with
other tools.
Um yeah so let me uh probably um talk a
little bit more about not just how the
fine tunes can be used to kind of um
adjust a particular model and make it um
tuned but how can we use it for
trajectories and tool calls which is
kind of more relevant today. Um so again
the models hallucinate right you see all
those headlines all the time about uh
some company tries to do something and
then kind of had to roll it back and my
kind of look at that is actually
summarization of news is a harder task
than than writing code because uh can be
tested right all of us who had the
proper um software engineering
background very much familiar with uh
what the software quality means and
being able to run that. And yeah, we in
Refact been adding all kind of different
tools uh for model to be run. And the
main idea uh of this getting feedback
from the tools is that we're allowing
the model to be able to run um auto test
or if we yeah by some reason you don't
have auto test you can try to compile a
project look at the warning llinters you
can even look at the execution logs or
even from browser. But the main idea
behind it as you get the uh the more
feedback the uh the the quality of the
um of the agentic work improves. Um one
of the results which we've done on the
poly globe benchmark um and again we use
the benchmark which was created by
founder of Ader and our difference of
how we tested it was actually allowing
the model to verify itself with a test
and what you seen here that the model
has drastically improved how it runs.
um um how it runs uh how it provides
results when it has the right tools to
verify itself. Now okay
um there is more tools on the horizon
unless you've been living under the rock
uh you already use MCP or you hearing it
uh or seeing the news about it every
day. So um while MCP is a an really nice
standard which now uh improves ability
to integrate all kind of different uh
different services in APIs, it's also um
a nightmare a nightmare for uh uh for
those who work with LMS to try and
manage this behavior. So um with MCP I
uh for the first time seen actually
error from um open eye about the uh uh
that the amount of tools uh has been
exceeded and believe it or not they have
128 tools which they support for tool
calls and even if you add 128 uh the
performance between selection of them is
would be really poor. So you need to
make a have a really um kind of um be
smart about what tools you add to the
models um even they if they fit the
limits right because uh there are now
enormous amount of trajectories and
models are struggle with all of them but
um this is kind of the example of of the
complex um setup right uh we expect the
model to be able to go to GitHub to uh
to get information about the bug We uh
want it uh our model to uh our agent to
go and uh get some additional data from
um let's say our production error locks
on sentry or whatever you use. Uh then
find the relevant unit test code uh unit
tests then um
uh replicate make sure that we add the
the right uh things to the unit tests
run them continue to make changes and so
on so forth. Those are really complex
trajectories and uh to make them right.
This is where the preparation of the
fine tunes from your um uh chats uh
becomes really really handy and you can
extract them from um saving your um
agent um logs. Um you can also which is
more relevant for on-prem and in our
case we uh we have support for onrem as
well. Uh on-prem is kind of a nice thing
because it has um uh it allow us to kind
of uh have a better security but the
problem with that is um the open models
which we run on prem are still not on
par with the models which we have um uh
on from closed providers. So one another
way uh to prepare our synthetic um data
is actually we can use a tool calls with
uh advanced model and cloth uh from
entropic and um uh from our experience
is today the most advanced model when it
comes to um working with programming
task and calling the the tools and um
what you can do is you can run um um run
number of chats run number of prompts
from your expected behavior, save how
Clot was um calling those tools and how
Clot was um um doing this work and then
from there you can create your training
set and then feed this training set into
uh let's say um your open model which
will be running on prem right you can
then um um fine-tune and use your
cheaper model um um use it on prim or
use it in your cloud environment. But
just uh for this uh trajectories have it
um uh cheaper. Yeah. Um yeah, I kind of
um going into the end of my prepared
slides. Um in general what I wanted to
um say is that today the fine tune um
becomes really really simple because the
tool set is already there which allows
to do a lot of stuff really really
simple. You don't need to look at the uh
TensorFlow uh uh code and understand
stuff. There's uh things are really
really simple today to uh be able to do
it as a developers. Uh the preparation
of data set is also improved because we
now have the advanced LMS which we can
um delegate the tasks to um prepare
synthetics data set for us. Um yeah, if
you haven't um yeah, go and try our
agent on Refacai or join our community
on
Discord. All
right, I have a question here. Also, AI
offers constant availability, judgment,
free support, and personalized
interaction tailored to each user. Um
not much of a question.
I have uh yeah, I can I can go through
the questions. Uh thank you very much.
First of all, I really really appreciate
the uh the the the the session, Nick. Um
yeah, got a couple of questions that
we've starred here. Question um from
from Richard uh Richard OC. Anyone know
of any good guies for fine-tuning on Mac
OS? Question. Yeah, I think I mentioned
that in my slides. I really like
transformer lab I believe they called.
Really really nice to uh nice tool. Uh
again open source have bunch of plugins.
I was really impressed with how it's um
has done. So definitely would recommend
and and uh I use it on my Mac. Yeah.
Awesome. Thank you. Uh couple of others.
Um interesting question here. This is we
always take this for granted when
someone says, "Oh, yes, this model was
trained on 15 trillion, whatever." Uh
what does that actually mean though when
we think about when we think about what
a token is, whether it's a word or a
half word. What does 15 trillion
actually look like? All right, you're
gonna make me do the mess in my head.
All right. So on on average uh I think
uh yeah I the token is roughly um uh
three or four symbols. Again depends on
the language depends on on the number
but it's it's in general the uh the
notion uh of all amount of um the the
data which gets into that the numbers
the numbers ridiculous. Right. So that's
uh you can think of tokens just as as
the um uh a number. Yeah. Yeah. Awesome.
Thank you very much. Uh I think that's
pretty much all the questions uh the
questions that we've got. Um in terms of
uh folks who are wanting to try out um
you know the tool what's the what's the
best way to get started?
Right. So um again and I was okay is
there a question or I'm not quite sure
what the what the questions which you
got there. Let me ask you your question
first. Uh so those who want to start uh
like I said we open source. So um uh
most of our code is uh available on the
website uh on on GitHub and uh finetune
of your codebase is the easiest um is
the easiest way to to use it. um
fine-tune of um of trajectories is
something which we don't have in our
open-source tool but it's something
which we supports our enterprise
customers with.
Awesome. Okay. Awesome. Thank you very
much Nick. Real pleasure to real
pleasure to have you join us and
appreciate you supporting the uh the
conference. I'm glad being here. Thank
you. Thank you.